Jessica C. Bylo Chacón,

EMAIL

bylochacon@gmail.com

WEBSITE

http://bylochacon.com

Strengths

Able to make complicated material understandable

Practiced manager of groups

Committed to continuous learning

Designer of creative & dynamic curriculum

Can stay on top of several projects at once

Independent and self-motivated

Experience Highlights

UNITED STATES HOLOCAUST MEMORIAL MUSEUM, WASHINGTON D.C.

Museum Teacher Fellow, 2007-2008

AMERICAN HIGH SCHOOL & FREMONT UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT

taught world history and other social science courses, January 2001-June 2008

created and taught a workshop on how to teach the Holocaust in tenth grade English and World History courses, April 2006

club advisor for Amnesty International, 2004-07 and Model United Nations, 2007-08

designed and organized a tenth grade World History Honors pullout program centered on literature circles and active reading and historical research

pilot of Small Learning Communities Program, integrating curriculum for tenth grade History, English and Biology, 2004-06

GLOBALEYES: NONPROFIT TO BENEFIT ORPHANS, WIDOWS & SCHOOLS, KENYA

board member, 2007-present

designed & implemented both the Turkey Trot to benefit AIDS orphans and the Swim Against Malaria to purchase anti-malarial nets for families with school-age children, at American High School, 2006 & 2007

created and organized the Swim Against Malaria to purchase anti-malarial nets for families with school-age children, at American High School, 2007 & 2008

RWANDA & KENYA: DEVELOPMENT AND RECOVERY

three weeks studying international development issues and the role of women in recovery of post-genocidal Rwanda with University of the Pacific International Studies Dean Dr. Margee Ensign, 2006

POLAND AND THE CZECH REPUBLIC: JEWISH RESISTANCE DURING THE HOLOCAUST

participant in an intensive three-week instructional tour for educators led by resistor and activist Vladka Meed, and organized through the Jewish Labor Committee and United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, 2005

SWIM COACH

American High School Junior Varsity, 2004-07 and City of Carpinteria Masters & U.S.A. Swim Clubs, 1998-2000

Education

SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY - MASTER OF ARTS, 2009

World History Since 1750, emphasis in teaching

SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY - TEACHING CREDENTIAL, 2003

Secondary Social Science Education

UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT SANTA BARBARA - BACHELOR OF ARTS, 2000

History

Jessica C. Bylo Chacón,

EMAIL

bylochacon@gmail.com

WEBSITE

http://bylochacon.com

Professional Development

UNITED STATES HOLOCAUST MEMORIAL MUSEUM, 2004-PRESENT

Fellowship Training Program, regional conferences and Belfer conference

FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY AT TALLAHASSEE, JUNE 2007

Holocaust Institute, eight days of lecture and discussion of various aspects of the Holocaust by professors and guest speakers

JEWISH LABOR COMMITTEE AND THE UNITED STATES HOLOCAUST MEMORIAL MUSEUM, POLAND TRIP REUNIONS, 2006-PRESENT

every-other year with three days of intensive discussion and lecture on new scholarship and methodology

HOLOCAUST CENTER OF NORTHERN CALIFORNIA, 2006-PRESENT

workshops have included: Echoes and Reflections Curriculum, Resistance During the Holocaust, Art as a Form of Resistance, Female Jewish Partisans

CALIFORNIA WORLD HISTORY PROJECT, 2006-2007

one week in June plus several weekends throughout the school year, learning how to teach with **complex instruction** methodologies

FOUNDATION FOR TEACHING ECONOMICS, 2004-2006

several week and weekend workshops on how to integrate economics education into history courses; have included units on the Soviet Union, Water, Capitalism and the Poor, International Trade

BUCK INSTITUTE, CALIFORNIA STATE UNIVERSITY AT HAYWARD, 2004-2006

workshops and lectures on teaching economics through problem-based learning